Finding Aid for Michigan Visiting Nurses records, 1896-2010
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Michigan Visiting Nurses records 1896-2010
Michigan Visiting Nurse Corporation.
85687 Bf.4 2
Michigan Visiting Nurses was created by the integration of the Visiting Nurse Association of Huron Valley into the University of Michigan Health System beginning in 1998. The Visiting Nurse Association of Huron Valley formed in 1980 with the merger of the Ann Arbor Visiting Nurse Association (AAVNA) and the Ypsilanti Visiting Nurse Agency (YVNA). The Ann Arbor association was formed in 1896 with the establishment of the University Hospital Circle of the King's Daughters, name later changed to the Ann Arbor Public Health Nursing Association. The Ypsilanti Agency was founded in 1941. Records include: Secretary's record books and files consisting of minutes, reports, and related organizational documents; scrapbooks; financial records; and subject files.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
11.3 linear feet
This record group (Donor No. 2435 ) was first deposited by the association beginning in 1948. Periodic additions have been received since then.
Periodic additions to the records expected.
The record group is open to research.
Michigan Visiting Nurses (MVN) is a home care provider of skilled nursing and rehabilitation services. It was formed when the Visiting Nurse Association of Huron Valley integrated into the University of Michigan Health System by becoming wholly owned by the Michigan Health Corporation (MHC) in December 1997. Michigan Health Corporation is the legal entity that allows the U-M Health System to enter into partnerships, affiliations, joint ventures and other business activities. It is a non-profit membership corporations wholly owned by the Regents. MHC transferred the Michigan Visiting Nurses to the University of Michigan Hospitals and Health Centers in 2007. In 2014 it was a department in the University of Michigan Home Care Services Division of Patient Care and Nursing Services. MVN services 13 counties in Southeastern Michigan.
In the early twentieth century, infections and epidemics like tuberculosis, diphtheria and influenza accounted for much of the nursing activity. Pre- and post-natal care were also emphasized. Gradually, as antibiotics and vaccines brought many illnesses under control, the focus shifted to home health care for the terminally ill and the elderly, hospital follow-up care and physical therapy, and children's health. This is reflected in the shift from charitable funding and independent operation of local nursing agencies to government (local and federal) and grant funding and consolidation of services at the county level to form a unified social service agency.
The Visiting Nurse Association of Huron Valley came into existence in April of 1980 with merger of the Ann Arbor Visiting Nurse Association and the Ypsilanti Visiting Nurse Agency. The Ann Arbor association traces its origins to the University Hospital Circle of King's Daughters and Sons, a charitable organization established in 1896 to help needy hospital patients. At first a private agency, in 1910 the organization began to receive some funding from the Ann Arbor City Council for its work. In 1913, the organization became an independent public agency associated with the National Organization for Public Health Nursing and called itself the Visiting Nurse Association. In 1918 the name was changed to the Ann Arbor Public Health Nursing Association (AAPHNA).
Through the early-to-mid 1900s the association developed more formal ties with the city of Ann Arbor and Washtenaw County, and as a result received more funding from these sources. In 1954 the AAPHNA became the Ann Arbor Visiting Nurse Association, and evolved into a social service agency funded by local government, grants, the United Way, and fees from private and governmental agencies such as Medicare, Medicaid, and Blue Cross. The association functioned independently until it merged in 1980 with the Ypsilanti Visiting Nurse Agency. At that time a new board was established with ten representatives from each city and four from Washtenaw County.
The Ypsilanti Visiting Nurse Agency began in 1941 with the employment of a half-time nurse whose salary was paid by the Community Fund Board. Service gradually expanded to cover more areas of the county, and by the 1950s three nurses were employed. Major funding by the Community Chest continued, while other sources, such as Medicare, Medicaid, and Blue Cross contributed to the budget. Physical therapy and psychiatric follow-up services were added during the 1960s. While operating independently, the Ypsilanti Visiting Nurse Agency was under the supervision of the Washtenaw County Health Department, who hired its personnel. The YVNA was dissolved when it merged in 1980 with the Ann Arbor Visiting Nurse Association.
The Michigan Visiting Nurses (MVN) records cover over 100 years of public health nursing in Washtenaw County, documenting the changing nature of this service and its associated agencies over the course of the twentieth century. The MVN records are organized into four series: Ann Arbor Visiting Nurse Association, Ypsilanti Visiting Nurse Agency, Visiting Nurse Association of Huron Valley, and Michigan Visiting Nurses.
Subjects:
Ann Arbor (Mich.); Visiting Nurse Association of Ann Arbor.; International Order of the King's Daughters and Sons. University Hospital Circle.; Michigan Visiting Nurse Corporation.; Visiting nurses--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Nurses--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Nursing--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Public health--Michigan--Washtenaw County.; Ypsilanti (Mich.); Visiting Nurse Agency of Ypsilanti.; Visiting Nurse Association of Huron Valley.
Genre Terms:
Scrapbooks.
- Ann Arbor Visiting Nurse Association
  The Ann Arbor Visiting Nurse Association, 1896-1980, series contains a nearly complete run of secretary's records, financial records, annual reports, statistical reports, nurses' daily reports of home and school visits, scrapbooks, materials relating to publicity and the National League of Nursing. Additionally, this series contains records pertaining to the AAVNA merger with the County Health Department in the 1940s and the Ypsilanti Visiting Nurse Agency in 1980. Details of the merger of AAVNA with YVNA to form the Visiting Nurse Association of Huron Valley are provided by the Merger Committee correspondence and reports from 1978 and 1979, the 1979-80 minutes of the Joint Merger Study Committee, and the merger agreement and plan of 1980.
  - Historical and background information 1896-1980 (Box 1)
  - Articles of Incorporation and Bylaws 1944-1980 (scattered dates) (Box 1)
  - Secretary's Records
    (record books to 1951, in folders thereafter)
    - 1896-1909 (Box 1)
    - 1909-1913 (Box 1)
    - 1913-1915 (Box 1)
    - 1920-1922 (Box 1)
    - 1922-1923 (Box 1)
    - 1923-1925 (Box 1)
    - 1925-1930 (Box 1)
    - 1935-1943 (Box 1)
    - 1944-1946 (Box 1)
    - 1947 (Box 1)
    - 1948 (Box 1)
    - 1949-1951, 1 folders; 1 volumes (Box 1)
    - 1952 (Box 2)
    - 1953 (Box 2)
    - 1954 (Box 2)
    - 1955 (Box 2)
    - 1956 (Box 2)
    - 1957 (Box 2)
    - 1958 (Box 2)
    - 1959 (Box 2)
    - 1960 (Box 2)
    - 1961 (Box 2)
    - 1962 (Box 2)
    - 1963 (Box 2)
    - 1964 (Box 2)
    - 1965 (Box 2)
    - 1966 (Box 2)
    - 1967 (Box 2)
    - 1968 (Box 2)
    - 1969, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1970 (Box 2)
    - 1971, 1 volumes (Box 2)
    - 1972 (Box 3)
    - 1973 (Box 3)
    - 1974 (Box 3)
    - 1975 (Box 3)
    - 1976 (Box 3)
    - 1977 (Box 3)
    - 1978 (Box 3)
    - 1979 (Box 3)
  - Financial Records 1918-1979
    - Account Book 1918-1930 (Box 3)
    - Insurance records 1920-1939 (Box 3)
    - Record of third party payments 1977-1978 (Box 3)
    - Income and expense statements 1978 (Box 3)
    - Budgets 1977-1979 (Box 3)
  - Reports
    - Annual reports with statistics
      - 1920-1924 (Box 3)
        (include photographs)
      - 1924-1926 (Box 3)
      - 1938-1939 (Box 3)
      - 1939-1940 (Box 3)
      - 1941 (Box 3)
    - Study of Public Health Nursing in Ann Arbor 1940 (Box 4)
    - Monthly service reports 1946-1947 (Box 4)
    - Community service series reports 1947 (Box 4)
    - Education committee reports 1963-1968 (Box 4)
    - Statistical reports
      - 1977 (Box 4)
      - 1978 (Box 4)
      - 1979 (Box 4)
      - 1979 (physical therapy) (Box 4)
  - Nurse's records 1912-1942
    - Various nurses 1924-1942 (Box 4)
    - Nurse Burrowes 1912-1913, 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - Nurse Binda 1930-1936, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Nurse Pino 1936-1937 (Box 4)
    - Nurse Stell 1935-1942, 2 folders (Box 4)
    - Nurse Jobson 1933-1942, 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Merger materials 1944-1980
    - Merger with County Health Dept. 1944-1948 (Box 4)
    - Merger (with Ypsilanti VNA) committee correspondence and reports 1978-1979 (Box 4)
    - Joint merger study committee minutes 1979-1980 (Box 4)
    - Merger agreement and plan 1980 (Box 4)
    - Merger documents 1980, 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - Merger closing book 1980, 1 volumes (Box 4)
  - Scrapbooks and publicity materials, 1936-1979
    - AAVNA 40th anniversary 1949, 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - AAVNA 50th anniversary 1959, 1 volumes (Box 4)
    - Scrapbook clippings
      - 1940s-1960 (Box 4)
      - 1960-1970 (Box 4)
      - 1971-1975 (Box 4)
    - Public relations materials 1969-1979 (Box 4)
  - National League of Nursing Materials 1959-1969
    - Reports 1959-1969 (Box 4)
    - Accreditation of community nursing services 1968 (Box 4)
- Ypsilanti Visiting Nurse Agency
  The Ypsilanti Visiting Nurse Agency, 1971-1979, series includes annual reports from 1941-1979, committee and board meeting minutes, board correspondence, news clippings and publicity materials covering 1956 to 1980, and a folder of historical materials. The series also includes minimal information regarding the merger with the Ann Arbor Visiting Nurse Association. Additionally, this series contains materials originating from outside of the YVNA. These include sporadic Washtenaw County Health Department and visiting nurse associations combined annual reports from 1944-1979, Washtenaw County Health Department guides and manuals, and County Nurse annual reports from 1930-1941.
  - History 1941-1979 (Box 5)
  - Annual Reports
    (bound vols.)
    - 1941 (Box 5)
    - 1942 (Box 5)
    - 1943 (Box 5)
    - 1944 (Box 5)
    - 1945 (Box 5)
    - 1946 (Box 5)
    - 1947 (Box 5)
    - 1948 (Box 5)
    - 1949 (Box 5)
    - 1950 (Box 5)
    - 1951 (Box 5)
    - 1952 (Box 5)
    - 1953 (Box 5)
    - 1954 (Box 5)
    - 1955 (Box 5)
    - 1956 (Box 5)
    - 1957 (Box 5)
    - 1958 (Box 5)
    - 1959 (Box 5)
    - 1960 (Box 5)
    - 1961 (Box 5)
    - 1962 (Box 5)
    - 1963 (Box 5)
    - 1964 (Box 5)
    - 1965 (Box 5)
    - 1966 (Box 5)
    - 1967 (Box 5)
    - 1968 (Box 5)
    - 1969 (Box 6)
    - 1970 (Box 6)
    - 1971 (Box 6)
    - 1972 (Box 6)
    - 1973 (Box 6)
    - 1974 (Box 6)
    - 1976, 1 volumes; 1 items (Box 6)
    - 1977 (Box 6)
      (pamphlet only)
    - 1978 (Box 6)
    - 1979 (Box 6)
  - Committee and board minutes 1970-1980 (Box 6)
  - Standing orders for staff 1958 (Box 6)
  - Board correspondence 1946-1948, 1960
    - Miscellaneous correspondence (Box 6)
    - American Cancer Society 1951-1956 (Box 6)
    - IRS 1948-1978 (Box 6)
    - Maccabees Insurance Co. 1945-1959 (Box 6)
    - Metropolitan Life Insurance Co. 1943-1952 (Box 6)
    - Veterans Administration 1951-1960 (Box 6)
  - Clippings and publicity material 1956-1980
    - 1956-1958, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - 1959-1963, 1 volumes (Box 7)
    - 1973-1980 (Box 7)
    - Publicity materials 1970-1980 (Box 7)
  - Merger report and bylaws 1979 (Box 7)
  - County nurse annual reports 1930-1941 (Box 7)
  - Washtenaw County Health Dept. and visiting nurse associations combined annual reports
    - 1944-1952 (Box 7)
    - 1953-1960 (Box 7)
    - 1973 (Box 7)
    - 1975 (Box 7)
    - 1976 (Box 7)
    - 1977 (Box 7)
    - 1979 (Box 7)
  - Washtenaw County Health Dept. guides and manuals
    - Guide for public health nursing service 1964 (Box 7)
    - Nursing procedure manual 1970-1974 (Box 7)
- Visiting Nurse Association of the Huron Valley
  The Visiting Nurse Association of Huron Valley, 1980-1982, series consists of bylaws, board minutes, and finance committee minutes.
  - Bylaws 1980 (Box 7)
  - Board minutes
    - 1980 (Box 7)
    - 1981 (Box 7)
    - 1982 (Box 7)
  - Finance committee minutes 1980-1982 (Box 7)
- Michigan Visiting Nurses 1967-2010
  The Michigan Visiting Nurses, 1967-2010, series within the MVN records consists of four subseries: Board of Trustees, Miscellaneous, Audio-Visual Materials, and Realia.
  - Board of Trustees 1997-2007
    The Board of Trustees, 1997-2007, subseries contains a list of trustees and semi-annually bound records of the group's activities from 1997-2007, including meeting minutes and agendas. The first several of these record binders illustrate the transition from operating as VNAHV to MVN.
    - List of Trustees (Box 8)
    - Records 1997-2001, 7 volumes (Box 8)
    - Records 2002-2004, 6 volumes (Box 9)
    - Records 2005-2007, 4 volumes (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous 1998-2010
    The Miscellaneous, 1998-2010, subseries contains publicity brochures, a printed PowerPoint presentation about the centennial anniversary of the organization, a patient admit packet, and a training packet.
    - Brochures 1999-2008 (Box 10)
    - Centennial PowerPoint Presentation 2009 (Box 10)
    - Patient Admit Packet 2010 (Box 10)
    - Training Binder 1998 (Box 10)
  - Audio-Visual Materials 1967-1997, undated
    The Audio-Visual Materials, 1967-1997/undated, subseries contains slides, photographs (some mounted), and a VHS videotape entitled, "Bringing the U of M Health Systems Home." Some of the decision making process for partnering with the University of Michigan can be found in the slide presentation. The mounted photographs and PowerPoint presentation from the Miscellaneous subseries are presentation materials for the organization's 2009 Centennial celebration exhibit.
    - Mounted Photographs for Exhibition undated, 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Mounted Photographs for Exhibition 1980s (Outsize) (Box 12)
    - Photograph -- Board members 1970s (Outsize) (Box 12)
    - Photographs undated (Box 10)
    - Slides 1967-1997 (Box 10)
    - Videotape-Bringing the U of M Health Systems Home (VHS) undated (Box 10)
  - Realia undated
    The Realia, undated, subseries contains two pieces of realia: a nursing bag and a Visiting Care uniform.
    - Nursing Bag (Washtenaw County Community Health) undated (Box 11)
    - Visiting Care uniform smock with pin undated (Box 11)